Guide to the Horse & Buggy Press print and graphic design projects, 1996-2017 RL.11339
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Horse & Buggy Press print and graphic design projects
1996-2017
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Horse & Buggy Press
Wofford, Dave
RL.11339
4.0 Linear Feet 7 boxes 185 items
Collection of fine art print and graphic design projects by Horse & Buggy Press in Durham, North Carolina, commissioned chiefly by non-profit organizations, small firms, individual authors and artists, and community events organizers. Formats include catalogs, broadsides, posters, newsletters, pamphlets and brochures, programs, and jacket and packaging designs for six audio and film recordings. Smaller projects include exhibit and book announcements, business cards, invitations, and menus for local restaurants. Chiefly consists of letterpress work, but there are also examples of offset and digitally printed items. Many projects involved the work of other artists and designers, and many were printed in limited editions. Content often includes poetry, prose excerpts, and quotes. Books and zines printed by Horse & Buggy Press have been separated from this collection and individually described for the Duke University Libraries catalog.
Arrangement
Arranged in these series: Broadsides; Posters; Catalogs, Brochures, and Programs; Small Commissioned Projects; and Audiovisual Packaging and Jacket Designs.
Biographical / Historical
The Horse & Buggy Press was founded in 1996 by Dave Wofford, and is based in Durham, North Carolina.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Materials may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use requires the donor's or artist's permission.
Original media are closed to use. Listening or viewing copies must be made for access to these materials.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Horse & Buggy Press print and graphic design projects were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase and gift in 2016 and 2018.
Scope and Contents
Collection of fine art print and graphic design projects by Horse & Buggy Press in Durham, North Carolina, commissioned chiefly by non-profit organizations, small firms, individual authors and artists, and community events organizers. Formats include catalogs, broadsides, posters, newsletters, pamphlets and brochures, programs, and jacket and packaging designs for six audio and film recordings. Smaller projects include exhibit and book announcements, business cards, invitations, and menus for local restaurants.
Chiefly consists of letterpress work, but there are also examples of offset and digitally printed items. Many projects involved the work of other artists and designers, and many were printed in limited editions. Content often includes poetry, prose excerpts, and quotes. Books and zines printed by Horse & Buggy Press have been separated from this collection and individually described for the Duke University Libraries catalog.
Commercial artists; Community arts projects -- North Carolina; Durham (N.C.) -- Arts and crafts; Graphic design (Typography) -- United States; Graphic design -- United States; Graphic arts -- United States; Letterpress printing; Printers -- Durham (N.C.); Sound recordings -- Album covers; Broadsides; CD-ROMs; DVDs; Posters; Sound recordings; Video recordings
- Broadsides, 1999-2017; 21 items
  Scope and Contents
  A collection of broadsides, chiefly letterpress printed in color, designed by Horse & Buggy Press for local events, individual authors, and for personal keepsakes. Sizes range from roughly 8 x 8 to 16 x 22 inches, with most in larger sizes. Many were printed in limited editions. Arranged chiefly in original order as received.
  - Maji Moto: Dispatches from A Drought, 2012, 4 items (Box 1)
    An accompaniment to the book of the same name, 2012. Four editions are represented here, each combining a single different photographic image with letterpress text. Giclee printed image, letterpress printed text. 190g William Turner paper. Each broadside was issued in a limited run, and is signed and numbered by the artist: "Dual Text," #24 of 28. "Paternal Care," #14 of 17. "Hazy Tree," #31 of 33. "Dead Giraffe," #3 of 27.
  - Lawson's Legacy: Nature Writing and North Carolina, 1701–2001 (2001) (Box 1)
    Edition of 300. Commissioned by the North Carolina Special Collections Library UNC as part of the conference celebrating the 300th anniversary of explorer John Lawson's trek across the Carolinas. Entirely hand-printed on the letterpress. Half of the edition was printed on machine-made paper, half was printed on hand-made paper produced at Antfarm (cotton fibers).
  - Durham Farmers Market: Celebrating the First Decade, 2001 (Box 1)
    #399 from an edition of 500. Engraving by Josef Beery. Entirely letterpress printed in five colors on paper composed of recycled and kenaf fibers. From the creator: "Instead of showing a cornucopia of produce like so many farmers market posters, I thought this image said 'harvest' as much as a type of food, and just like an ear of corn is composed of many small kernels, a farmers market is made up of many small farmers."
  - Poplar Forest: Photographs by Rob McDonald, 2016 (Box 1)
    Accompanied the Poplar Forest fine press book published in 2016.
  - Book + Art (Artists' Books at Duke + UNC), 2010 (Box 2)
    Commissioned for a dual library book and arts show. The broadside was a keepsake gift for authors who had work in the show. Horse & Buggy also designed a poster for this event (not included in this collection). Entirely letterpress printed in five colors from hand-set type on bamboo/cotton blend paper.
  - Pupille Amate, 2015 (Box 2)
    Italian lyrics from opera seria Muzio Scaevola, 1721, by Giovanni Bonancini and Paolo Antonio Rolli, with English translation. Entirely letterpress printed in four colors on 25% hemp, 75% post-consumer recycled content paper.
  - Rubenstein Library Dedication, 2015 (Box 2)
    Commissioned for the Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript library renovation dedication, Duke University, Durham, NC. Image was printed digitally, letterpress-printed black and blue text.
  - The Nature of Craft and the Penland Experience, 2004 (Box 2)
    Designed for the 75th anniversary of the Penland School of Crafts in Asheville, NC by one of its artists. Accompanied the book release of the same name. Entirely letterpress printed.
  - For Deb Wong, on the Occasion of Her Leaving Duke University Press / Ode to Typography (Neruda), 2010 (Box 2)
    Commissioned by Duke Press's book design department as a present for a retiring staff member. Title is from a poem by Pablo Neruda. Waterfall collage by Amy Ruth Buchanan, overall layout by Horse & Buggy Press. Entirely letterpress printed on Somerset printmaking paper. Edition of 25.
  - A Good Problem, 2011 (Box 2)
    Title comes from a poem by Michael Chitwood. Entirely letterpress printed. Small run of broadsides for a Mother's Day keepsake.
  - A Dakini Night Poem, 2009, 2 items (Box 2)
    From a poem by Traktung Rinpoche, honoring the twentieth anniversary of his realization as a guru. Entirely letterpress printed from hand-set type. Edition of 100. Two different color schemes (one white, one black, one copy of each).
  - Goodbye Little Rock n' Roller, 2015 (Box 2)
    Features excerpts from a speech by singer/songwriter/author Marshall Chapman, commencement speaker for Duke University's MFA/EDA Program. Features lyrics from her songs, one of which she wrote with Terri Sharp, and a short narrative about infinity and the arts. Letterpress printed.
  - 102 Doors, 1999 (Box 2)
    This vernacular-inspired design was created for architect Dwayne Poovey, from Antfarm studio, who put together an exhibit on typology. Offset printed in an edition of 200.
  - Stories Only Happen to People Who Can Tell Them, Allan Gurganus drawing, 2014 (Box 2)
    Limited edition (130/280) keepsake commission by the North Carolina Writers Network as they honored Allan Gurganus as keynote speaker/featured author for the annual conference. Quote is from Oldest Living Confederate Widow Tells All.
  - Birdhouses, 2017 (Box 7)
    Created to celebrate the 10th anniversary of the Birdhouses book (2007). Gourds on a line photograph by Rob McDonald, giclee printed. Text is by Cynthia Reliant. Limited edition of 54.
  - The Fabric of Durham, 2017 (Box 7)
    Three portraits of Durham citizens by Christer Berg, giclee printed. Limited edition.
  - The Fabric of Raleigh, 2017 (Box 7)
    A broadside with three portraits of Raleigh citizens by Christer Berg, giclee printed. Limited edition.
- Posters, 2001-2016; 14 items
  A collection of color posters designed for a variety of local North Carolina Triangle events and small firms, with a mix of offset and letterpress printing. Sizes range from roughly 8 1/2 x 10 3/4 to 14 x 18 inches, with most being larger in size. Many were printed in limited editions. Arranged chiefly in original order as received.
  - Bending Space: George Rousse and The Durham Project, 2007 (Box 2)
    From an edition of about 150, with three different designs. For this month-long art event, the French installation artist Rousse created eleven different installations in older buildings throughout downtown Durham, North Carolina.
  - Politics & Prose: City of Midnight Skies, 2001 (Box 2)
    This event promoted the world premiere of the Horse & Buggy book City of Midnight Skies. Entirely letterpress printed from hand-set type.
  - Ms. Film Festival, 2004 (Box 2)
    Entirely letterpress printed on chipboard, in a limited run of about 100 copies.
  - Pinata Anchor of Hope, 2005, 2 items (Box 2)
    This poster publicized a Sherri Wood art installation project; each of the two copies is signed on the back by Wood. Entirely letterpress printed in five colors. Numbers 7 and 8 of a limited edition of 325.
  - Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel Visiting Filmmaker Series: Laura Poitras, 2012 (Box 2)
    Commissioned by Duke University Libraries and digitally printed in an edition of 150.
  - Green Frame: A Month Long Exposition in Reclaimed Materials, 2010 (Box 2)
    Digitally printed poster for an art auction fundraiser for Builders of Hope. All art was made from repurposed building materials, thus the use in the poster's design of blue painter's tape, and the background image of the Horse & Buggy ink mixing table.
  - XX Merge: Twentieth Anniversary Music Festival, 2009 (Box 2)
    Poster was designed by artist Maggie Fost, who also made the maquette featured as a central image in the poster and which represents the Cat's Cradle music venue stage in Carrboro, North Carolina. Offset image with letterpress printed text, edition of 500.
  - Ninth Street Derby, 2013 (Box 2)
    Digitally printed edition of 100. Horse & Buggy Press donated the design for this cycling event in Durham, NC. Photographs by Ben Knowles.
  - Durham Central Park Pavilion Dedication, 2007 (Box 2)
    Small run of digitally printed posters for the Durham, NC market.
  - Click! Triangle Photography Festival, 2016 (Box 2)
    Digitally printed edition of 200 produced for this Durham, NC month-long photography festival.
  - 40th Annual Centerfest, 2014 (Box 2)
    Digitally printed edition of 200. The design plays on the colors and seven stars on the city of Durham flag.
  - Durham Critical Mass Bike Ride, circa 2009 (Box 3)
    The design on this small flyer was a collaboration with a Durham School of the Arts student, Matthew Brondoli. Other tag lines included "The evolution will not be motorized." Edition of about 200 copies, digitally printed. The owner of the press, Dave Wofford, helped organize these monthly Durham bike rides.
  - Writers in the Ring, 2015 (Box 3)
    Commissioned for the closing event of the Durham, NC Read Local Book Festival. Event was organized by Chris Vitiello, who also suggested the theme for the poster, which was billed as "a creative writing fracas" and "a no-hold-barred writing showdown."
- Catalogs, Brochures, and Programs, 1998-2017; 26 items
  A mix of catalogs, brochures, and program guides created chiefly for local non-profit organizations, small firms, and community events, many of them performances or art exhibits. There are also two jazz radio station newsletters. The largest group is a run of program guides for the Durham, North Carolina's Full Frame Documentary Film Festival, most of which are over 100 pages long.
  - WSHA jazz radio station newsletters, 1998, 2 issues (Box 3)
  - Collin Beggs Timber Framing business brochure, 2000 (Box 3)
    Created with letterpress text and offset photographs. The blank right hand pages was meant for a single full color image to change over time.
  - Click! Triangle Photography Festival brochures, 2015, 4 items (Box 3)
    Designed by Horse & Buggy, these 2015 and 2016 guides to the Durham Full Frame Documentary Film festival were offset printed at Theo Davis in Zebulon. Two copies for each year.
  - Meals from the Market, 2008 (Box 4)
    Offset printed guide to a local Durham, NC food festival held in 2008. Over 20 pages.
  - Green Frame program guide, 2010 (Box 4)
    Commissioned for a month-long exposition in reclaimed materials, with associated auction night and Raleigh City Museum exhibit. Printed by Theo Davis.
  - Duke Gardens Annual Report, 2015 (Box 4)
    Full-color annual report is 63 pages long and features color photographs of the Gardens. Offset printed.
  - Reynolds Price Reading Series, 2015-2016, 2 items (Box 4)
    Two programs, including the inaugural event in 2015. They feature digitally printed interiors with hand printed covers, and contain drawings by Duke students, memorial tributes, commentary and biography of the featured reader, and photographs of Price from his papers in the Rubenstein Library at Duke.
  - Migrant Musicians: Filipino Entertainers and the Work of Music Making, 2013 (Box 4)
    Booklet reproduces a thematic social media dialogue sponsored by the Center for Art + Thought in Los Angeles. The authors, writers, and artists in this series are Theodore S. Gonsalvez, R. Zamora Linmark, Karen Tongson, moderated by Sarita Echavez See. Hand-sewn, letterpress printed covers with digitally printed interiors. Limited edition of 150.
  - Full Frame Documentary Film Festival program guides, 2009-2016, 8 items (Box 4)
    These program guides typically run over 100 pages and are in full color, offset printed by Theo Davis in Zebulon, NC. Contents include an entry for each film submitted to the festival, with accompanying summary, film-makers and producers, and a thumbnail film frame; includes advertising and festival screening locations and associated events. Covers feature a scene from a films in the festival.
  - Duke University Press catalogs, 1999-2016, 10 items (Box 5)
    A collection of Duke Press bi-annual catalogs and one book sale catalog. There is also a catalog for the Duke University Film and Television Studies Program.
  - Full Frame Documentary Film Festival, 20th anniversary program, 2017 (Box 6)
- Small Projects, 1996-2016; 118 items
  A large variety of printed work, including menus for local restaurants, wedding and birth announcements, book launches and exhibit announcements, memorial programs, and business cards. Also includes a group of publicity materials, letterhead stationery, and one certificate award for Horse & Buggy Press.
  - Watts Hospital Hillandale Artwalk & Night of Light and canned food drive yard signs, 2003 (Box 2)
    Yard signs made by Dave Wofford for a Durham, NC neighborhood association arts event. Although most later versions are machine-printed, a few are the original letterpress signs. The Night of Light graphic was created by W. A. Dwiggins.
  - Menus, 2000s, 8 items (Box 3)
    Following from the Horse & Buggy Press owner's past restaurant work, he created many menus for local restaurants in Durham and Raleigh, of which these are a sample.
  - Watts-Hillandale neighborhood bumper sticker, 2000s (Box 3)
  - Exhibit announcements, 2000s, 59 items (Box 4)
    Most of these items are one-page cards announcing installations, exhibits, and similar arts events. There are some duplicates. Many were created for the Bull City Arts Collective in Durham, North Carolina; the owner of Horse & Buggy Press, Dave Wofford, curated over fifty guest artist exhibits in the Collaborative from 2007-2016.
  - Book announcements, circa 1996-2016, 11 items (Box 6)
    Created for Horse & Buggy Press book projects, several of these announcements feature hand-printing on the letterpress. Some duplicates are present.
  - Menus, 2000s, 5 items (Box 6)
  - Other small projects, 2000s, 25 items (Box 6)
    File includes business cards, two memorial programs, marriage and birth announcements, and other small cards and invitations. They are a mix of letterpress and digitally printed work. The memorial programs are for artist George Bireline (d. 2002), and David Warren Wilson (d. 2015).
  - Horse & Buggy publicity and promotional materials, 1996-2016, 9 items (Box 6)
    These items include the first Horse & Buggy Press letterhead stationery, as well as the press's first brochure (brown cover with phrase "Letterpress printing for the Jet Age"), which was entirely hand-printed in an edition of 500. The second version of the brochure is also present. Includes an AIGA award given to the press for one of best books designed in 1999 (An Elizabethan Bestiary: Retold). The 1999 books in print catalog features letterpress covers, xeroxed interiors, and is hand-sewn.
- Audiovisual Packaging and Jacket Designs, 2001-2009; 6 items
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original recordings are closed to use; listening or viewing copies must be made for access. Please contact the Rubenstein Library Research Services before coming to use these materials.
  Audio (music and spoken word) and video recordings with packaging and jacket designs created by Horse & Buggy Press and other collaborators. Some were issued in limited editions. Original media is restricted to access.
  - Sound of Singles Sings Seger, circa 2009 (Box 6)
    This 7-inch single record album jacket design is letterpress printed in three colors on chipboard. Released in a numbered edition of 300, and distributed by 7&T Records in Durham, NC. The acoustic covers recorded by Gerald Schoenherr are of two classic rock songs by Bob Seger, "Turn the Page" and "Beautiful Loser." The LP is also accomnpanied by a CD.
    Original media closed to use; a copy must be made for access.
  - What We Have Lost: New & Selected Poems, 1977–2001, by Jeffery Beam, 2001 (Box 6)
    Two-volume spoken word recording CD, in limited run of 500 copies. The jacket design is a mix of offset and letterpress printing, with drawing by David Terry.
    Original media is closed to use; a copy must be made for access.
  - Blackbirds, Bottle Caps, & Broken Records: Environmental Artist Bryant Holsenbeck at Work, 2009 (Box 6)
    DVD of 15-minute documentary film produced by the Center for Women & Ministry in the South, Durham, NC, filmed and edited by Margaret Morales. Film is of artist Bryant Holsenbeck, who uses reclaimed, recycled materials to create her community art projects. Cover drawing is by Bryant Holsenbeck, with the packaging and jacket design by Horse & Buggy Press.
  - Three CDs of work by musician Kenny Roby, 2002-2003 (Box 6)
    CD of Kenny Roby's Rather Not Know, 202, numbered edition of 300; and two CDs of the same artist's recordings, Memories & Birds, in two different package designs, one of which is #10 of 500 copies, signed by Roby.